Inventory of the Ron Kovic papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ron Kovic papers
1973-1975, 2011-2013
2014C40
Hoover Institution Archives
2 oversize boxes, 797 digital files (1.2 linear feet, .001 GB)
Writings and slides relating to the Vietnam War. Includes the manuscript of the book by Kovic, Born on the Fourth of July (New York, 1976). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Kovic, Ron.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
A Vietnam war veteran and anti-war activist, Kovic wrote the autobiography Born on the Fourth of July published in 1976. A film of the same title, directed by Oliver Stone and starring Tom Cruise, was released in 1989.
Scope and Contents note
Writings and slides relating to the Vietnam War. Includes the manuscript of the book by Kovic, Born on the Fourth of July (New York, 1976).
Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Slides (Photography).
- Digital files, 2011-2013 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains digital surrogates of Roger Steffens' photographs of Ron Kovic, his friends, and family, during the time when Kovic was writing "Born on the 4th of July." Digitized versions of the photographs were created by Steffens between 2011 and 2013.
  - Roger Steffens 73-75 pictures of Ron Kovic's manuscript, 1975
  - 352 pictures of Ron Kovic, 1973 July - 1975 September
  - 32 pictures of history of "Born on the 4th of July,", 1973-1975
- Large print of Ron Kovic at typewriter, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Note written by Roger Steffens describing the contents of the Ron Kovic papers, 2013 September 25 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Notes and poetry from Ron Kovic, including letter from Lynn Nesbit, his agent, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Album of negatives from Roger Steffens of time spent with Ron Kovic, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
- "Born on the 4th of July," typed manuscript with handwritten annotations, 1973-1975
  - Part 1 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - "Growing Up," handwritten dictations of Ron Kovic taken by Roger Steffens about early childhood, 1975 August 8
    - "Growing Up Blind in America," typed draft of chapter on early childhood; drawing on back with handwritten note to Roger Steffens signed from Bob Waddell, wife, Shannon, and son, Zephyr, undated
    - "Coming home from the war/ 1st time," Kovic's recollection of returning home from Vietnam; incomplete, typed with handwritten edits, undated
    - 3A: One page excerpt about Kovic's childhood, watching war films and pretending to be Marine with childhood friend, Richie, undated
    - "Chapter Three: Bootcamp," handwritten dictations of Ron Kovic taken by Roger Steffens about training and reflections on boot camp, 1975 August 9-10
    - Chapter 3: Draft on time in bootcamp; incomplete, typed with handwritten edits, undated
    - Untitled draft on Kovic's time at home while on leave from training with Marines, undated
      Includes detailed recollection of sexual encounter at a folk concert in his former high school gymnasium; handwritten.
    - Untitled draft on Kovic's lament over loss of intimacy after being paralyzed; handwritten, undated
  - Part 2 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 4B: Later draft of untitled chapter on Kovic's lament over loss of intimacy after being paralyzed; typed, handwritten annotations, undated
    - 4B: Untitled draft regarding Kovic's internal conflict over paralyzation, undated
      Includes anecdote about night of heavy drinking; typed with handwritten annotations.
    - 4C: "Village of the Sun," draft of chapter on Kovic's time in Mexico; incomplete, typed with handwritten annotations, undated
    - 4D: "Room 17: Hospital II," draft on Kovic's hospital stay after breaking right leg; typed with handwritten annotations, undated
    - 5A + (4E verso): "Getting Arrested," handwritten draft on Kovic's arrests and comraderie with fellow activist veterans; typed draft on Kovic's first anti-war demonstration in Washington D.C., incomplete, undated
    - 5A: "Getting Arrested," draft on Kovic's arrests and comraderie with fellow activist veterans, typed with handwritten annotations, undated
    - 5B: Untitled draft on Kovic's arrest at his first anti-war march, handwritten and incomplete; "The Trial," draft of chapter (on verso) about Kovic's trial after arrest in front of Nixon's headquarters, incomplete, typed with handwritten annotations, undated
    - 5B: "Insert to P12, ARRESTED," handwritten and typed drafts on Kovic's arrest at march and booking into jail, undated
    - 5B + 5A on verso, "Getting Arrested" written at Chateau Marmont, Los Angeles, CA, handwritten draft of Kovic's arrest at anti-war rally; "Kent State," typed draft of Kovic's time immediately after Kent State, first speech at high school about the war and traveling across the US to California with his friend, Kenny, 1975 August 24, undated
    - 5D and unused: "Last Chapter," "Being Born," draft of Kovic's reflection on his life after combat, paralyzation, and activism, typed with handwritten annotations; "Dream" handwritten draft of Kovic's last chapter, incomplete, undated
    - 5D: Much unused, five attempts at final chapter, handwritten and typed with annotations, undated
  - Part 3 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - 6A: "Dream," abstract writing about "The Last Patrol" convoy of anti-war veterans, undated
    - 6A: "The Last Patrol," handwritten and typed drafts of chapter on convoy of anti-war Vietnam veterans travel to the 1972 Republican National Convention in Miami, Florida, undated
    - 6B: "Shouting Down the President," draft of account of Kovic and fellow veterans protesting against Nixon and Agnew inside of the 1972 Republican National Convention, undated
    - 6B: Not used, handwritten draft of ending of "The Last Patrol" chapter, undated
    - 7A + 7B: "The Corporal," handwritten and typed drafts recounting the incident on Kovic's second Vietnam tour in which he accidentally killed a Corporal in his battalion, undated
  - Part 4 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 7C + 7D: Untitled drafts regarding the events on Kovic's second tour culminating in his injury, undated
    - "Adjusting," single page from draft on being home after injury and hospitalization, undated
    - "First Tour," unused drafts on Kovic's first tour in Vietnam, undated
  - Part 5 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Chapter 1 + Parts of 3, 4, 5 C on verso: Handwritten and typed drafts of first chapter in book detailing Kovic's injury on the battlefield, includes annotations, 1973 August 23
    - 2A + unused: Drafts regarding Kovic's time in hospital and returning home, undated
  - Part 6 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 2B + unused: Drafts on Kovic's time spent in the hospital after his injury, undated
    - 3A: "Growing Up," handwritten and typed drafts of Kovic's reflections on childhood, undated
    - Notes and guide to numbering of chapters and drafts, undated